Hello, welcome everyone. It's March
28th, 2025 and we're in quarterly roundt
number
one. We are a participatory online
institute that is communicating,
learning and practicing applied active
inference. You can find us at the
following platforms and links. This is a
recorded and archived live stream.
Please provide feedback so we can
improve our work. All backgrounds and
perspectives welcome. Video etiquette
for live streams is as
follows. Head over to
activeinference.institute to see our
static page and links from there.
Take a look at this slide for a lot of
stable short links and entry points into
different
activities. Okay, we will have a lot to
talk about today in this round table. We
will talk about institute projects, then
ecosystem projects, then talk about some
speculative designs for 2025 and then at
the end we will check the live chat for
questions and comments. First though,
let us introduce ourselves. So, I'm
Daniel. I'm the president and one of the
co-founders of the institute and I'm
here with Alexandra. Greetings. Uh, I am
the VP of the institute and uh a new
officer starting in 2025 working along
with Daniel uh to further the goals of
the institute.
Cool. Okay. So let us head into it and
again looking forward to people's
comments written in the live chat which
we'll get to at the
end. Let's start with some updates at
the institute
scale and begin as beffits the year and
moment with some
generative
visualizations. So while this from 2023
and versioned since provides more of a
structural anatomical view here with a
few quick prompts, we see a bit more of
the PI policy selection, planning as
inference, all that good stuff happening
amidst a thriving vibrant ecosystem with
kind of
dollyesque and graphical models, rivers,
nature, different kinds of synergetic
structures,
geodessics, flowers and trees, life,
tables, chairs, people, all that
happening in the ecosystem. So there's
going to be some technical details,
there's going to be a lot of nittygritty
at times, but this is the bigger picture
and vision that together with the
institute as just one player in a
broader ecosystem, we can make some
awesome things happen.
2025.activeinference.institute is kind
of a history in real time page.
It's a good entry point nested under
history page and it archives what's
happening this year, what is upcoming
and as the months fly by, we move them
down to the bottom of the page and in
doing so document what's happening as it
happens through many of these short
links like ecosystem or others. you will
find
yourself moved into this living koda
document which has many many many nested
pages and it can be a lot. So couple
tips. First off, you can download a PDF,
you can go to print and PDF, export it,
you could upload it to your favorite
Perplexity or or similar service to have
a direct chat with it. Um and and that
chat affordance is also provided at the
institute and ecosystem page. So you can
have that kind of interactive discussion
with the
documentation and at a top level that
document which thankfully and gladfully
is in the most updated shape that it's
ever been contains pretty much one
section on the
institute pi and then another main
section on the ecosystem itself. So
within the institute part you can learn
who and what are we what has happened
here why it's important to support it
mission vision values principles and
projects all these different things that
have happened and and are happening and
then out in the ecosystem we'll continue
to do our best to curate at the topical
and at the project scale what is
happening out there and in doing so
provide unique services for people who
want to ask questions
like what is the status of active
inference and robotics or law or
economics or society or category theory.
totally concise, valid, relevant
questions that we look forward to having
people. As with all activities, step
into stewarding in this fractalized way
these important domains so that with
stable links and reference, there's an
entry point that's kind of always
welcoming, alignable, and soft landable
for people who want to start learning
and applying as we aim to
support. Getting to some of the bodies
within the
institute. So we have convened
our third or fourth scientific advisory
board. Um we could check it's the
largest of the SABS assembled and we've
had monthly meetings in the past months.
Just this week we had two great
meetings.
Uh the scientific advisory board is our
informal guidance board and they're
focusing their activities first off
showing up and participating as
individuals in however they see fit and
also focusing their activities on
supporting the research fellows program.
supporting mentoring, providing
mentoring especially to the
interns. Providing review and feedback
for example on projects, applications as
well as go no-go type decisions or
critical feedback for different projects
or grants that we might apply
for. Mission and vision, keeping that
year round bonfire discussion about what
what do we need? What does the ecosystem
need? How can we do
what we should do, be who we should be,
and helping to seek out, forge, forge
partnerships, which we'll talk more
about, but relationships with other
organizations, providing different kinds
of synergistic win-win type outcomes
between the institute and what what we
can do, what we are, and with what
organizations are doing out there. So
looking forward to working more this
year with this really awesome and
multifaceted SAB. So thank you to
everybody um who has already stepped in
and and showed up for what we've gotten
started with the
SAB onto the formal bodies of the
officers and the board of directors. So
on the officer side, officers are
operational
administrators. They consist of myself
as the president and treasurer and
Alexandra Mccava as the vice president
and secretary. So as the president, I
aim to provide overall leadership,
direction and support the institute
programs and as treasurer support the
financial responsibility and
accountability.
Alexandra as the vice president shares
in those
responsibilities of the president and as
secretary provides logistical support
with a focus on knowledge engineering.
On the board of directors we have
convened a new cohort with some new
characters and some returning BOD
members. John Clippinger, Blue Knight,
Alex Vatkin, Daniel Freriedman, Mike
Smith and Vladimir Bowen. And each of
the board of directors are looking to
and already playing really important
strategic roles, helping us expand the
time horizon of where we're looking and
where we're
going. It is not too early to think
about being an officer or board of
director in a future year, possibly
2026, possibly later. Learning more and
getting involved is the best way to
reduce your uncertainty about whether
these roles might be apt for you. It's
also useful to get involved and start to
build your history at the institute and
ecosystem have that open- source
footprint and find a co-creative synergy
with your work and development. So these
are volunteer positions at this time
though I hope that they can find more
support in the future and thank you to
officers and
BOD. All right, getting into some of the
programs. research fellows is a program
that we began last year with these
affiliated researchers and developers.
There are currently five research
fellows in the game right now and you
can find from fellows short link more
information and link out to each of
their products projects and they're each
working on super fascinating activities
and periodically share in through
measurements and through live streams
and other kinds of reporting what
they're working on across super
different domains. I'll also just note
that at the donate short link, the drop-
down menu enables support to a given
research fellow project. So these are
all works in progress and evolving. At
the organizational level though, we hope
to pattern out this possibility of
people who think that a piece of work is
really exciting and they want to support
it. Kind of like having a name on a
building at a department at a university
or supporting a given project have the
oversight capacities for spinning up to
arbitrarily high and exciting levels.
the work of these research fellows and
providing this rotating and evolving
space where we provide them support
ranging from the affiliation and the
email address on through supporting
their research and and their time and
involvement. So JF, Anna, John, David
and Robert, thank you for being some of
our earliest research fellows and for
for carrying out your work which is
improving a lot of the aspects of the
applicability and scope and the the
breadth of active inference. So cool
work. Looking forward to sharing more of
these a little bit more will come up in
later updates in this round table and
also live streams and and the updates
just from following these people's work
separately.
partnerships. So partnerships are
structured relationships consensual
confirmed between the institute and
other organizations who are looking to
make meaningful visible custom impactful
contributions to the active inference
open source ecosystem.
support the sustainability and the reach
of the institute through financial
and/or inind
contributions. Organizations who are
looking to upskill and accelerate their
own processes of learning and
application looking to connect with our
community and the growing field and
talented and enthusiastic interns to
form regional language and sector level
collaborations. any intersectional
subsets of those and to provide critical
strategic input and guidance to the
institute. As of last year, we had two
partners, first principles first and
Newman games. And this year we have
announced and developed our official
partnership with lazy dynamics who lead
the development of RX infer pro and
co-supervvis RX infer through the
open-source community reactive bay
frameworks for building active inference
and basian agents. So if this is an
interesting possibility and a pretty
open one at that then definitely reach
out. there are a lot more things
happening in the ecosystem which is
super exciting to see. And so whether
it's a lab established research academic
lab or one that's just beginning or
whether you're a startup or looking to
have some active inference
implementations or birectional
conceptual or technical transfer
happening within an established company.
lots of opportunities to gain some of
these benefits and that link will share
more
information. To the topic of
philanthropy and
support, it is 2025, our fifth year of
all volunteer operations.
To be totally honest and clear as I am
massively appreciative to be able to be
such in this round table we're at a
critical juncture in how we proceed in
our structure and function within the
ecosystem. So just to give some of these
details and then explain the generative
AI over here, we are registered in
Delaware in the United States as a
501c3 taxexempt educational
nonprofit. And we made that strategic
move because we believe that
philanthropic and grant type support is
and and would be essential as we build
towards a more impactful and sustainable
organization. We have a main
donate.active.institute
Institute PayPal link which any amount
could be provided through that channel.
There's also the donation affordances on
Substack the newsletter and through
YouTube. And more broadly we seek some
patrons or sponsors or partners who
might like to provide a type of 0ero to
one
like relationship or help us connect or
communicate with individuals or
organizations who could help us in that
way. If you believe in the past,
present, and future value of what we're
doing at the institute, this is a key
direct ask with immeasurable relevance
and leverage for our work in the years
to come. This is really the time to at
least consider it and consider what?
Well, here in this sort of two roads
diverge, Robert
Frostian
style, there's sort of two archetypes.
This is just speaking personally with
some ways about how I've been thinking
about this over the past months and and
years even and and where it all fits
into my own life
too. Two possible fractal distinctive
paths for where and how the institute
proceeds. Here on the right, the city on
the hill and the accumulation of
resources and the institute as a router
and inputs of resources, outputs of
resources and a density in the center,
possibly routing millions of dollars,
uh, arbitrary numbers of zeros of
different currencies in different ways
with this extremely professional
nonprofit
possibility and structure that exists
and is recognized
globally. On the other side of this fork
is something like a Taurus or a donut
where enrichment is occurring healthy.
It's a healthy donut. Enrichment is
occurring in the periphery in the
shoulders and in the ecosystem around
the institute and the institute retains
this absolutely priceless special unique
character that I believe it has today of
a
volunteerist potlock type valitional
convening.
Yes, with communication
channels however not the same formal
resourcing that is required to have city
type infrastructure. So while there's
many kinds of distinctions and gradients
that that I believe that we can uh have
it both ways or be in a quantum superp
positionality purely from an
administrative
perspective 2025 is going to be a really
critical year in at least whether we
take steps towards yes we are going to
be working with partnerships and
philanthropic donors and companies and
grants that want to see and want to be
part of the journey towards having this
civilizational level infrastructural
centralization construction even with
broad productive lands
beyond. And also in what ways or what
other vehicles or what higher level
understandings is this doughut style
where we keep space and wildness in the
center and still support
through enriching and improving people's
connectivity, weaving fabrics,
supporting fundraising rounds, finding
people the different opportunities that
are going to support their lifestyle in
their location and then with one or 10
or 30 hours a week out of an abundance
they may still want to volunteer or be
involved in the institute but again
that's different than the city and all
that it entails and I like this image
too because it it highlighted there are
many branching paths in the end though
we are just going to walk forward so not
to overly dichotoize it but I wanted to
share that because that is something
that I'm thinking about and the decision
has been easy and made for us in the
previous years with the low income and
low outflows. This is uh a pivotal year
though in understanding and formalizing
that a little better. So many many ways
to help and and hopefully people provide
their their input and support on that
avenue. Okay, getting to some of the
project level updates. First the
projects within the institute and then
getting into some of the projects that
are happening in the
ecosystem. So the
obsidian.activeinference.institute short
link will take you to an obsidian sync
front end.
Obsidian.md is a
open-source plain text knowledge
engineering style that is also going to
come up a little bit later in this round
table as well. And that short link is a
live interactable version of the
information that's at this GitHub repo
called
cognitive and we can go to it.
This has been the result of some
conversations and development over the
last few
months of having
interactableworked ways to learn and
apply active inference and guides and
all kinds of ways to explore different
topics developing learning paths. So
once the template for the learning path
was out there, it became very possible.
Okay, what what's the entry point and
the birectional course from pragmatism
or robotics or cognitive security or
whatever it happens to be developing
these learning paths in and out within
the context of this broader repo which
provides a lot of support for learners
as well as for autonomous agents who are
processing this information. And you can
clone the repo and access it locally
graphically explore it or you can use
the obsidian sync. So the idea is to
support interactive modular interlin
resourcing and documentation for
learning and applying active inference
as well as adjacencies related to math,
neuroscience, computer science, etc.
Use generative AI wisely for every last
mile of learning accessibility and
applicability in terms of bringing it to
people's preferences and pallets with
language settings styles level of math
notation formatting all these things and
be part of building these interoperable
methods for graphical
exploration using simpler wiki and
Obsidian style hyperlinking backlinking
as well as well as using more advanced
graphical database
techniques. So cool new learning
resource enabled by cursor and
generative AI and providing a lot of
resources and on-ramps and off-ramps and
ways to apply active inference that
weren't there just a couple months
ago. In the active inference textbook
group, we are active with cohort 7 who's
in the second half of the book and
cohort 8 who has begun the first half of
the book. This is the still only active
inference textbook that's out there, the
PAR, Pazulo, and Fristen 2022 textbook,
which has also been translated into
several languages over the previous
years. Um, I'd like to especially
appreciate Andrew Pasha who has been
facilitating the
second later in the day meeting of the
textbook group. It's it's been awesome
and the people who watch the recordings,
the people who are showing up, it's been
a great epistemic experience and we
continue to revisit classic questions,
bring new questions onto the table and
it remains to be a great
attractor. And also we're always pulling
back and seeing where does this textbook
group fit in with this unfolding
ecosystem of learning resources and
experiences. And so there's a lot of
ways in which again with wherever and
however people want to volunteer or find
some sort of supported way to get
involved. There's a lot of ways in which
we could modularly start to think about
some mitosis or transfer learning. Maybe
another textbook group for another book.
We plan to do so for Sanjie Nam Jooshi's
book when it's available. Maybe there's
some other books that having a a
discussion group around would be useful.
uh something around application
specifically math learning group all
these kinds of things which which we can
explore and in that potentiality without
anyone jumping in to to lead one of
those efforts we dwell and attract to
this big convergent space that's really
welcoming really bringing in people from
different backgrounds all around the
world different time zones who are
wanting to just learn more about active
inference and also check in weekly see
what's happening with the institute and
hear about other opportunities through
there in audiovisisual production we
continue to produce open- source
audiovisisual materials and release them
disseminate them into the active
inference ecosystem so we've had a
pretty interesting first quarter we've
had a handful of guest streams and a
model stream, a math art stream, and
several active infer ant streams.
Looking at the guest streams this
quarter, what really reflected on me was
how possibly with the almost exception
of the slime mold and philosophy, Matt
Sims guest
dream, almost all of these relate in a
way to humans and computational and
cognitive
interactivity, whether through
probabilistic models and their
integration with LLM
or more explicitly like human computer
interaction and cognitive experience
design questions. So that is I think an
emerging niche and and interfacial
relevance for active inference in that
sort of connective tissue and the space
within and between different kinds of
synthetic intelligence systems amidst a
broader sort of panccognitivist
understanding in human and and social
technical
ecosystems. I'll make this call one more
time. If you have these skills or you'd
like to learn some of these skills like
production, audio and visual related
education, communication, any other or
some interest that you can't even put
your finger on, but you're watching this
live stream, please consider getting
involved. It is just me organizing these
live streams and carrying them out.
There are a ton of other opportunities
both in front of the facilitation and
also behind the scenes and curating
papers, inviting people, developing
materials. They don't have to be live
streamed. They don't have to be in
English. They can be with a different
format. Like if you have ever felt, oh,
if only there was a shorter video or one
from this perspective, you've
identified where your preferences could
be either dissipated away by just
updating, oh well, it doesn't exist,
say, or maybe it's a call to action and
it's the right moment for you to help
step in to make that kind of material.
So, there's a ton of ways. It would be
really fun to have more audio and visual
production and also connect this with
different languages, different
backgrounds and learning paths. So if
that sounds something that is
interesting, it can be done in a really
timeboxed efficient way. You could be an
intern or it could happen outside of an
internship. But hopefully this is an
exciting opportunity to be involved in
producing material either on the
institute channel or even just
supporting you in your own channel or or
ways of disseminating. So, it's been
super fun to have done five or 600 live
streams over the years, and I'm really
seeking some
other contributors who want to pick up
that approach and just do it in a
different way. No need to recapitulate
anything that I've done, which has been
just
whimsical in many cases. It's just about
what is the real need and what would be
something that upskills who wants to
contribute and provides them meaning and
value in the moment. So super fun
project doesn't require technical
expertise in active inference. Having
somebody who wants to learn or just
wants to explore can be the question
catalyst that brings and creates these
unique materials. But you know 100
people in a room all asking the same
question in their head but then no one
says it or no one makes a video doesn't
reduce too many uncertainties. So I hope
that some people who are interested in
these topics and whatever formats they
think could be meaningful or valuable,
let's literally do it. Do some new
things during this year just like Darius
with insights and Shana with Math Stream
sort of led and templated last
year. Okay.
Um, a few weeks ago we found out that we
did not receive funding for this
project. However, this enabled us to
publish it as a pre-print and now
excitingly share it with you. So, this
was a project that Alexander and I
thought we would write up. Increasing
the accessibility and applicability of
active inference generative playbooks
and open source summer school curriculum
development.
The letter of funding interest was
submitted to Dana Frontiers program in
pursuit of funding several promising
activities. The application was not
funded. We have uploaded it as an
open-source artifact here seeking
participation and resourcing for these
and other projects in due time, place,
and fashion. The goals of this project
were to develop generative playbooks for
open-source cognitive modeling,
providing educational materials which
empower communities to engage in active
inference as learners, researchers, and
practitioners, and to develop an open
source curriculum and pilot a summer
school in 2025 to integrate our
innovative online approaches with
in-person opportunities, providing
accessibility in this cutting edge area
and embedding community perspectives in
the future of neuroscience.
So, if either of these avenues are
interesting today, March 28th, or in a
future time, that's what it's here for.
That's why we preprint and show our work
along the way. Some of these things can
pop up in the strangest of ways. Maybe
for you, maybe for someone
else. Getting to some of the institute
research
projects. So activities for the TNB, the
theoretical neurobiology group have been
active this year. I'll read the
objective and the overview for this
group. The TNB group has been fostering
interdisciplinary research and
collaboration for decades. Our mission
is to advance the understanding and
application of active inference, a
theoretical framework developed by
Professor Carl Fristen. This is achieved
through regular online meetings
featuring presentations and discussions
which may include theoretical
frameworks, empirical data and its
analysis, simulations and mathematical
development. We welcome contributions
and perspectives from diverse fields
including neuroscience, mathematics,
machine learning, psychology,
philosophy, medicine and biology.
The TNB for a long time was hosted
through the affiliation and
professorship of Carl Fristen at UCL in
London and now is hosted at the
institute. So we look to work more with
the excellent chairs of the TNB who I
will go to the website
and scan over
here. So going to the TNB short link
will pop you to this page where you can
link over to the YouTube
channel. You can click over to the
meeting, learn more about how to
participate, Ry, Miguel, Peter, Robert,
and Kristoff. and also see a little bit
about some of the ways that we're
working
together between the institute and TNB
to make these extremely unique very
fascinating and
historical
convenings something that feeds back
into the active inference ecosystem and
and gives a platform and a place for
people to present their work in really a
unique way. So, thanks a lot to the TNB
chairs and to Carl Fristen and everybody
who's participating in these very cool
TNB
meetings. So, in the RX and FUR
projects, we've had a lot of fun. We've
continued to meet weekly with a lot of
participants coming through,
facilitation by myself and Frraasier and
sort of guest star fractal facilitation
popping in throughout. We discuss a
variety of topics from late breaking
updates in RX infer versioning to
minutia of GitHub issues and examples.
We pull back. We think full stack. We
talk a lot about engineering and about
systems
engineering. So pop in to the weekly
meetings which are currently on
Thursdays at 13 UTC in the Discord. A
week ago, we had a great stream with
Lazy Dynamics and some guests along Bert
De over here and
Frasier and talked about RX and Fur and
what Lazy Dynamics is doing about it.
And in the RX and Fur short link, we
continue open- source development and
documentation, building examples, asking
questions. So, really exciting, really
fun. just yesterday even some uh fun
advancements building off of an example
that they provided using flux to do
neural network modeling within Julia.
episode we had chaotic system hooked up
to a neural network with an RX infer
probabilistic model on top and talking
about interpretability usability all
these different ways in which RX infer
and the examples that are being provided
week after week are building a lot of
contact points with contemporary machine
learning methods. So really exciting
times and and work
continues. All right, little bit about
ecosystem projects. So the measurements
that I'll share in this next section
come from active participants at the
institute. people who you'll see
chatting a storm in a discord or you
might see facilitating or joining a
textbook group, people who are involved
in watching the stream as well as people
just in the broader community as we seek
to convey and norm hey there's this
measurement opportunity. There's this
short link
measure.activeinference.institute
institute where if you submit I saw a
bird or I wrote a paper or whatever it
may be, we want to with with your
consensual permission in that form, we
want to bring that and give it
visibility within the round table like
is about to happen here and also in the
newsletter. So the idea is streamlined
gradients of reporting and ecosystem
information flows grounded in active
inference and free energy principle
cognitive systems concepts and design
patterns and
modules. The naming for this prepare and
measure is based around the quantum
active inference sort of duty cycle.
Preparation is setting up the inquiry
and your interpretive
frame. Requesting support from the
institute and the ecosystem. Hey, I am
about to do this. I but I need this
amount of support first or I am going to
do this no matter what. Here's what
would be awesome support or here's a way
that the institute or others in the
ecosystem could be supporting this
journey, this inquiry that I'm about to
head out upon. and then measure
reporting on what happened for for your
own logging and to share back into our
broader community. Reset for the next
preparation. Share your next steps and
your learnings and ways for people to
find out more or get involved and again
to get permanent visibility in the round
table and in the newsletter. So this is
kind of like whatever the interface is
the screen the cubit whatever it may be
that's happening we are communicating
across
interfaces through space through time as
we know it and we're seeking to balance
these sort of operational considerations
of streamlined accessible information
flows meeting people where they're at in
terms of the information they want to
share and the information streams and
types that they want to receive with
some really really exciting technical
ways to compile the information and
rebroadcast it. But really at at the
heart of the matter is people wanting to
share in their updates and care about
what other people are doing in the
ecosystem. So let's look at some of
those. Okay.
Research Discovery Engine Project Gen
25. There's some links
here. We're building a platform that
leverages advanced AI, including LLMs,
topic modeling, agents, and active
inference to accelerate and increase the
impact of scientific research. This will
be available on mobile and the
web. This quarter, we applied for
funding, launched a website, created a
GitHub, produced a product roadmap,
began integrating several functional
databases and AI oriented back-end
services, and began collaborating in
real time and asynchronously.
And in terms of the the impact of this
work, just reading from the form that
was submitted by the team, it opened the
doors to existing active inference
researchers and will provide all
researchers or anyone epistemically
curious to explore novel areas, ideas,
and topics. By employing a variety of
solid paradigms in category theory and
aensic modeling, we aim to dramatically
increase the rigor of existing and
potential contributions. We will employ
a custom score tailored for each user
that evaluates research along several
important
dimensions. And the team here is Andrea
Ferris, Andrew Pasha, Austin Cook,
Benedict Waldick, Daniel Freriedman,
Janna Theiru, Marcus Apparos, Shagger
Ramen, and Vladimir Bon. And I'll just
zoom in on this
image. So, our funding application is
pending for this project and it's been
volunteer work with some of it being
shown through the links in the repo on
this page and a lot of it is uh also
developing on the
sideline. Um so, a lot of fun topics.
We're working on a paper to milestone
and then we will reduce our uncertainty
about what to do next when we find out
about the current pending grant. But one
of the big topics here and inspired by a
lot of the work happening with the
knowledge graphs was thinking about
different sorts of epistemic foragers.
Whether a learner engaging in discovery
and education or whether a researcher
looking to evaluate a field or make
their own kind of
contribution. How to have these
different views and
elements on the path to discovery both
new to the person like education and new
overall like a research discovery.
using a variety of tools like embeddings
and concept maps to understand what
areas are
unexplored. Be able to do path finding,
wayfinding, waym making within different
kinds offormational spaces and also
connect that to real people and
collaboration
opportunities in a really accessible way
so that people can see where they're
atformationally, socially, etc. and have
support in their journey. So, it's been
really awesome to work with this team
and I hope we can continue and find
support for
it. Okay, Jonathan Shock from Shock Lab
at the University of Cape Town in South
Africa asked me to pass on this
post-doal opportunity. So for
researchers who might be interested in
joining a dynamic team working on active
inference in relation to affective
consciousness, this position offers an
exciting opportunity to work at the
intersection of computational,
cognitive, and affective neuroscience
and artificial intelligence in
collaboration with leading researchers
in the field including Dr. Ryan Smith
and Cheryl Vanhoof. So, and it's
co-advised by professor Jonathan Shock
and Professor Mark Souls. So, pretty
cool opportunity. Thank you, Jonathan,
for sharing
that. Cauldra Kurser, an intern has done
a very cool update over the last several
days. So, I'll load up the
website. This is what the website looks
like.
interactive
website
terms are embedded kota panels from our
active inference ontology document. So
culture
wrote the prototype of the idea
developed in my master's thesis finally
materialized into a website. I built the
website using Obsidian and Quartz 4 and
hosted it via GitHub pages. Most of the
included theoretical sentences included
thus far are from millillage at all
2021, a mathematical walkthrough and
discussion of the free energy principle.
I just arrived at expected free energy
and I'm planning to include the low and
high road from par at all textbook next.
So what happened? launched the website
the first 40 sentences first
presentation of the idea and the
prototype in Leipzig Germany and this is
really fascinating so I hope people read
about Gul's work and see what's going on
um the ontology topic modeling term
modeling is used as a sort of background
for these for the
terms accuracy action and so on but
where the really interesting
philosophy meets the possibility of
rhetorical analysis and and pedagogy is
with these sentence fragments. And so
learning about that and about that sort
of next level bringing together of
topics into these sentences and how we
can link to sentence fragments as nodes
is going to be awesome for the
applicability and for the accessibility
of these topics and and putting them in
a place where it can be like yeah does
active inference reduce uncertainty
where is that claim supported or not?
this kind of claims analysis done within
a really um careful thoughtful way. So
thank you culture for sharing it and for
this epic
work.
Okay. Harshel Shaw Satyaki Maitra and
Roit Shenoi from uh the project in
active inference approach to autonomous
navigation. They are high school interns
and they wrote, "We have completed phase
one of our project, submitting to our
local science fair and winning second
place in our category. We have completed
a poster summarizing our project below
and a g GitHub showing the code so
far. We learned how to present active
inference to people using examples and
technical mathematics. We applied active
inference to autonomous navigation in a
short period of time. The work expands
active inference into the field of
navigation and
hardware. We access numerous papers and
help from people within the institute.
We are asking now how can we move into
more realistic simulations and hardware
with active inference. So this was a
great project. Hopefully the poster
conveys
that this was outstanding professional
work from a very young and enthusiastic
team.
and they're making epic advances in
hardware and software open-source
robotics with active inference. So, they
are flying over the target and thank you
for sharing this exciting
update. Just a few more short updates
from the project humanity story of an
uncertain self. Shaggar Ramen reports
formalized the myth of objectivity
hypothesis and that was pretty cool to
see because that is building upon some
work that was published a few years ago
and cool to see the work continue. So
thank you Shaki Jeff Clatcher research
fellow from symbolic cognitive robotics
project just to give a little snapshot
this is what it looks like in discord to
be getting getting those real time
updates from JF um just sharing a couple
days ago that a discussion with Elliot
Hower who's on the SAB led to some
changes and linking to these concepts so
it's like it is epic to see when we are
able to connect. It can be streamlined
and effective. It can be of mutual
interest. It can be technical. It can be
purely personal. It can be operational.
All these different ways to connect and
then report back in in a relevant way in
the right
time. How did that update our model? How
did the updating of our model lead to
changes in what we're doing? And so JF
has been a longtime stalwart contributor
and is doing awesome work with this
project. And so for people interested
in symbolic cognitive robotics to not
say too much more than that, check out
the GitHub and in the Simco Cog robotics
channel in the
Discord.
Okay. All
right. So last uh section before the
live
chats, speculative directions for 2025
and/or beyond. So as with all things
these are conditional on interest,
resourcing needs, emergence, volunteer
contributions and resourcing, funding
and grants, attentional regimes,
developments in the ecosystem,
partnerships, all kinds of things. It's
literally conditional on everything,
conditional on world model. And we're
thinking, okay, we've reported on what
was. We talked about measurements that
came in before today from what has
happened in the first quarter of this
year and now we find ourselves in this
present moment like now how to or what
to and that's a tactical topic and we
can think about that in terms of policy
inference. And here let's also look a
little further to what if you know the
institute is not something whose future
is set in stone. So this is an opening
for the conversation in due time as you
come across this. What would be of
epistemic and pragmatic value for
you? What else should we consider and
co-explore?
You know h how do you want to be
involved with some of these
avenues with the very real possibility
that your contribution even if you do or
don't feel like an expert in this or
that might be part of the uh go or no go
on something that could be life-changing
for someone else or yourself. So first
the fifth applied active inference
symposium in 2024 in November we had the
fourth applied active inference
symposium and it was pretty epic. There
was about 30 hours of video with many
many
presenters talking about active
inference applications, tool
development, exciting directions, open
source repo, lots of great materials and
uh what about this
year? We don't have a date. We don't
have a co-organizing team yet. So, it's
just planting the seed early and earlier
than we have in the past that we're
seeking co-organizers who want to check
out the template for how we organized
last year and modify that sponsors,
partnering organizations and also
presenters or
facilitators who want to be involved in
this fifth applied active inference
symposium.
So you can be affiliated with another
organization and just show up as a
person. You don't need to have any kind
of affiliation or even previous
contribution to the institute. It's
super fun participatory opportunity for
co-organizing. So being a part of the
planning process and having your input
make a difference in how many people
will be able to improve their
applications of active inference. Again
super fun opportunity. I hope that
people who are interested in these
channels of contribution get in
touch. Okay.
Next, we are in the process of setting
up this DI nodes publishing affordance.
So if you'd like to help as an editor or
a platform usability designer, there
could be amazing opportunities for
people who are interested in durable
accessible modern publishing,
credentiing, cryptographic attestation,
decentralized science, DESI
integrations, peer review, all these
different kinds of topics. How do we
make from the first person
perspective reading and writing to the
literature modern and more available and
useful? And how do we in include these
new
technologies for publishing and
asserting
and all all kinds of cool DI processes.
So, this is a pretty blank slate and
it's a pretty cool emerging platform.
So, again, if if somebody wants to
explore being an editor and and having
some kind of stewardship over this
platform or just being one of the early
publishers on
it, let us
know. Okay. Next project and direction
from knowledge engineering. So little
bit of history in 2022 with Blue and
R.J. we did uh systematic literature
metaanalysis on free energy principle
and active inference literature and then
we transform that data into KOD and we
developed some low code interactive
visualizations about ontology term use
uh different authorship patterns and so
on. That was that was the end of
2022. Now in this year we plan to be
working with Sanjie Namoshi and the TNB
chairs and also maybe you to develop a
modern interface for accessing searching
and gleaning relevance from the active
inference literature. So again, whether
you think, "Oh, I I have a uh my own
tagging system for the literature and I
think that that could be useful to bring
into play, or I've done something
similar, or I'd like to learn how to do
something similar, or I'm the kind of
person who wants to be using that
system, and I want my user experience to
be really important in that
design." This is a great place to get
involved. All right. And then last of
the directions for now before I'll check
the live
chats. Big
picture, we are moving towards robust
modular approaches for applying active
inference. And building a little bit on
how I framed this at the end of last
year, we can think about a lightweight
stack and a sort of heavy stack, but
it's not about their mass, but just as a
metaphor on the light stack is something
that can be run in a browser, run on
mobile, no code and low code, multimedia
affordances, high interactivity, looking
at the
surface, a lot happening under the hood,
but something that is lightweight and
accessible presented on the screen. And
that lightweight stack for learning and
for simulating active inference systems
under the hood would be running a heavy
stack. And the heavy stack could also be
used on its own. So developing the light
stack and presenting that is really just
one of the functionalities of the heavy
stack which would be looking into the
future of conventional and
unconventional computing and also
learning a lot from the open science
open-source and neuroiming communities.
For example, the way that Neurode
Debbian is like a Linux distribution for
for neuroscience computational uh
methods, the Neuroesk
containerization strategy, NGC museum
archival repositories, and then thinking
about the implementations of active
inference. So from the implementational
whether we're on a digital or some kind
of
non/postdigital processor on through the
operating systems that we're running.
Take it or leave it. Maybe the one that
you have is fine and you can enter in at
the containerization. Or maybe you don't
want to use containerization and you
want to enter in at the level of really
well doumented version source code. or
maybe you have your own source code on
the side and you want to enter in at the
level of documentation and methods for
the inference
implementations. All all of that is part
of this stack which is realistically
going to be
outside of the development
uh path for for example any given
research lab or startup. So this is I
think one of the key ways in which we're
going to be able to add a lot of value
and catalyze a lot of research and
application projects in the space is by
having documentation and direct work on
these tools. So that when people think I
want to apply active inference, whether
they pull back to the education, how can
I learn it or who could I find that
knows it or whether they want to just
enter in at the level of well what are
the tools, what are the examples, what
are the packages, all those kinds of
questions that can be something that is
not
like square zero, but rather there's
some really strong methods. Uh, for
example, we we have curated examples of
several dozens of active inference
implementations in different languages
and and those could each have
uh a website that is enacting that
example in the light stack and linking
to a deployment in the heavy stack. Just
to again show that with different
payloads, different languages, it could
be possible to deploy these different
examples. Those could be cross
referenced with the ontology. So like
this example
is deep time planning and affective
inference and then this one is affective
inference and attention and then those
kinds of things can be
recomposed. So again big picture this is
valuable software tooling and
applications that would have stewardship
and expertise convened at the institute.
We could be providing trainings,
examples, guide books, applications,
interfaces, simulations, maths,
visualizations, templates, and
workspaces for education, research, and
service. Actton for serve. We could
continue the refinement of core active
inference functionality for example with
a cross referenceable tech tree along
with some of these non-technical or not
active inference technical topics like
norms of use and intellectual property.
We can support collaboration and and the
varied works happening at the institute
and ecosystem with networking and making
sure that people who want to use this
stock can find expertise and
enthusiastic contributors. Just like
there are ways if you're wanting to
learn or apply Linux, there are
different kinds of consultancies and
groups and open- source efforts that
make that something that can be
professional and adaptive.
we can integrate with data integrity and
cognitive security
methods and I really hope that more
information on this will unfold in the
year to come hopefully with everyone's
participation and
support. So that is it for that section.
I'll close to this slide that we have
always closed on and uh review the live
chats. So if you're
watching please write any comment or
question in the chat and uh I will go
through them and then we will end it
here. Hello upcycle club. Thank you for
the support.
Morgan writes, "TNB meetings have been
great." Thank you,
Morgan. Ander,
hello. So, I'll wait one minute just to
see if anyone writes any specific
questions.
Okay. Blanket at
activeinference.institute for
emailing.
So, enter through any of these portals
or email us and you will be well on your
way. It's a participatory situation.
We're looking for people who want to
step in and be involved and help out
with this work and make it be what it
can be or make it be other than what it
already has been. So, I hope that this
has been an informative stream for our
human and non-human listeners and I will
see you around. Till next time, thank
you.